The A-zone radio-controlled
bridge-busting bomb,
TV-guided unmanned drones,
even extraordinary bombs guided by bats,
or a complex system of optics linked to
a pigeon.
These are the top-secret weapons
designed in World War II to give the US
military a decisive advantage over its
enemies.
The start of a weapon system that would
transform the way wars are fought.
>> You could see it track you. It would
have been like watching an animal watch
you.
>> Right now on World's Weirdest Weapons,
with rarely-seen secret footage, we go
behind the scenes of the race to create
what would become known as the smart
bomb.
Ever since the military began dropping
bombs, the top brass has been searching
for [music] a way to make them more
accurate.
To find a weapon that would give them
the edge and allow them to strike
targets from distance with deadly
precision.
And the need was never greater than in
the aftermath of Pearl Harbor.
December the 7th, 1941.
Pearl Harbor in Hawaii is devastated by
a Japanese surprise attack.
Almost two and a half thousand Americans
are killed, and the United States
immediately enters the war.
America is desperate to strike back,
and top military minds, as well as some
of the most creative [music] civilian
inventors from all over the country, get
to work on how to do it.
The aim, to hit Japanese targets with
devastating firepower and fearsome
accuracy.
One man who thinks he has an answer is
Pennsylvanian dentist and keen inventor,
Dr. Lytle Adams.
He believes he's spotted a major
Japanese weakness.
Their buildings are made largely of
flammable wood, bamboo, and paper, and
he thinks he knows how to put a guided
incendiary bomb inside each and every
one of them.
If it works, he could raise Japanese
cities and industry [music] to the
ground.
17-year-old high school student Jack
Coofa first hears about the idea while
working part-time in the LA County
Museum of Natural History.
>> A jolly man came into the museum where I
was working in the afternoons.
His name was Lytle Adams.
His proposition was so outrageous,
so crazy, that
it just didn't seem
possible.
>> In an age before computer-guided [music]
weapons, how does Adams intend to hit
Japan?
Bats.
He wants to strap bombs to a million of
them and drop them over Japan.
>> The reason uh
Doc had come to us was because my uh
mentor
was a bat authority. Name was Jack Van
Bloaker, and Van Bloaker thought about
it for a while, and he says, "You know,
basically the biology of it
makes sense."
>> The plan isn't as outlandish as it
sounds.
There's science to support the theory.
Bats are strong, able to carry their
young as they fly. So, maybe they can
deliver a small incendiary bomb.
There are millions of them. So, while
individually they might not be able to
hold a large device, together they could
be devastating.
And they hibernate. So, if kept in
carefully controlled conditions, they
should be easy to transport and handle.
Most importantly, in daylight bats seek
out dark crevices. Perfect for getting
incendiary bombs into cracks and under
the roofs of Japanese buildings.
By chance, Adams is a friend of Eleanor
Roosevelt, the First Lady.
And on January the 12th, 1942, he takes
his idea to the White House.
>> Ah, here it is.
Now, here we have
a letter from
Franklin Delano Roosevelt to his aide,
Colonel William J. Donovan.
This man is not a nut.
It sounds like a perfectly wild idea,
but is worth your looking into. You
might reply for me to Mr. Adams' letter.
F. D. R. Franklin Delano Roosevelt.
>> With Roosevelt's backing, the top secret
operation, code named the Adams plan,
gets the go ahead.
Adams sets about recruiting his team.
Jack Coofa and his boss are inducted
into the Army Air Force
>> [music]
>> and immediately join the project.
>> The unit consisted of eight or 10 of us.
Von Blocher was the
>> [music]
>> Batman.
I was the Bat Boy.
>> They head for the bat caves of [music]
Texas and New Mexico.
It's there they meet bat enthusiast
17-year-old Denny Constantine.
>> They explained that they were on a
secret government project
and that they couldn't give me any
details.
Up until now I've been considered a
crazy kid and studying bats.
But now suddenly my government needs me.
And who am I to say no?
>> No one was allowed to ask us any
questions. We had [music] this top
secret paper and anything we said or did
was
to be accepted.
So, that was sort of a
a free-wheeling credential to be
carrying in your pocket.
>> In absolute secrecy the team starts
searching for the right species of bat
for the job.
They need to find out exactly what
they're capable of and work out how best
to handle them.
>> So, this is the bat that was used for
the bat bomb project.
It's known as uh the
Mexican or Brazilian free-tailed bat
and you can see it
the free tail that extends southward
between its legs.
>> Each evening millions of Mexican
free-tails leave the caves of Texas and
New Mexico in search of food.
They're easy to catch, but if the
project is to have any chance of
success, the team have to be able to
contain and manage them.
They must find a way to induce the bats
to hibernate.
>> I quickly learned that uh I could
put a bat in the refrigerator and it
would go into a state of hibernation.
But then I could reverse that situation
by putting them into a pre-warmed oven,
and they would quickly warm up, and boy,
were they ready to move.
>> Next, they must discover how much the
bats are able to haul.
>> We had to test the bats for how much
they could carry. Now, you have to find
out how much it can't carry, and then
you work down from there. That's what we
did. So, the first bat we dropped from
there fell like a stone.
>> Tests reveal the tiny half-ounce bats
can carry up to twice their own body
weight, but the smallest incendiary
device available at the time weighs 2
lb, 30 times heavier than the bat could
carry.
It's a major problem.
To try to solve it, one of America's top
scientists, renowned Harvard chemist
Louis Fieser, is brought on board. His
job, to design an incendiary device
light enough to be attached to the bats'
bellies, [music]
but destructive enough to set buildings
ablaze. His plan is to use his recent
invention,
napalm.
>> Napalm
is gasoline that is gelled. It actually
looks quite like the gel that you
sometimes get instead of toothpaste.
And it's a semi-solid form of petrol.
>> That little bit of napalm, it had
something mixed with it that sort of
made it splash out and throw flames away
from it.
Big timber like this could light them on
fire. It was incredible what that tiny
little bomb could do.
>> But for the incendiary device to work
effectively, it needs more than just
napalm.
>> Building an incendiary bomb that's small
isn't as easy as it seems. With an
incendiary bomb you have to have the
burnable material, but then you need to
have a fuse and somewhere of igniting
the fuse and timing the fuse. It's quite
complicated.
>> Fieser needs to design a tiny timer that
will ignite the napalm at exactly the
right moment. Each and every one must
work without fail. There's no room for
error.
>> The timer had to be perfect. Just think
of this. I mean, if if there was an
actual plane load of these bats
with
uh with uh 10,000 bat bombs in the plane
and just one of them failed,
it would it would be a catastrophe.
>> But gradually Fieser perfects his tiny
bomb and the team are almost ready to
start testing. But before they get the
chance, Fieser has a disaster in the
lab.
1943,
the hunt for the smart bomb is well
underway and one team of scientists are
preparing to test their very unlikely
weapon.
A bomb that will unleash a million bats
armed with incendiaries to set Japanese
cities ablaze.
But before they get the chance, one of
the designers has a disaster in the lab.
>> The Air Force had sent us some
photographers down. They wanted to see
what happened with a real bomb.
>> Fieser, who just developed the tiny
incendiaries complete with timer fuses,
is keen to show them off.
But while he knows his bombs, he's no
bat expert.
>> Fieser took out a half a dozen bats and
clipped on bombs. The bats came out of
hibernation, they flew away, and within
uh 20 minutes we had
six fires going.
>> The fires ripped through the [music]
base, destroying barracks and a control
tower.
The Air Force immediately loses interest
in the project.
But, it's not over yet.
>> To us, it proved it worked.
And to a Marine Corps general who was an
observer there, it proved that it
worked.
>> Convinced of the bat bomb's potential,
the Marine Corps launches Project X-Ray,
and the team starts putting the
finishing touches to their weapon.
Doc Adams has designed a purpose-built
bomb shell.
The Fifer container will hold over 1,000
bats snoozing in separate compartments
on 26 [music] trays.
The bomb will be dropped from high
altitude.
At 4,000 ft, a barometric device deploys
a parachute, and the outer casing
simultaneously falls away.
The trays open like an accordion,
[music]
freeing the bats from their
compartments. Each one then acts as a
launching platform, allowing the bats
time to wake up.
As they take flight, a hair-thin wire
arms the incendiaries, primed to go off
in 30 minutes.
In December 1943
at Dugway Proving Ground, Utah, the bat
bomb is readied for testing.
To be dropped over a replica Japanese
town built in the desert.
>> There was quite a crowd there, mostly
statisticians and just, you know,
high-ranking observers.
>> The weapon is taken up in a bomber and
released.
It works perfectly.
The bats disperse and hide under eaves
and in attics just as expected.
Observers get to work comparing the bat
bomb to conventional incendiaries.
[music]
There may have been skepticism before,
but what they find is impressive.
In conventional bombing missions, the
aircraft could carry enough normal
incendiaries to start up to 400 fires.
But there's a lot [music] of wastage.
Many bombs would miss the mark and cause
no damage at all.
But the test finds a bat bomb-equipped
plane could start 4,800
separate fires, 12 times as many.
And everyone in a flammable and
inaccessible place.
The bat bomb gets official approval. The
plan to drop it over Japan in September
the following year. But the months go by
and the team hears nothing.
>> I mean, if we were going to really pull
this off,
the time was was fast approaching when
it would have to happen.
And a million bombs would have to be
manufactured.
The clock was ticking.
>> [music]
>> But it isn't to be.
Out of the blue in February 1944, the
project is canceled.
Nobody can explain why.
The team don't know it, but research
into another top-secret weapon is
nearing its conclusion.
One that will end the war in Japan
entirely.
The atom bomb.
>> I always regret
that we didn't get a chance [music] to
do it.
>> But American scientists don't give up on
animal-guided smart bombs.
Some believe they're the answer to the
biggest challenge in aerial bombing.
How to hit a precise, small, high-value
target with pinpoint accuracy?
>> From the very beginnings of air power,
the problem of accuracy emerges. You've
got two choices, essentially.
Uh you can either fly in low, so you can
see the target, but you're much more
likely to be shot down, or you can try
and hit the target from high altitude,
but the mathematics of how to get a bomb
dropping from your fast-moving aircraft
onto what is now a little dot on the
ground are vastly more complicated.
>> In the early years of the war, hitting a
target from altitude means dropping a
large number of conventional bombs and
hoping one will hit.
It means committing massive amounts of
bombers and their crews,
and many won't come back.
>> High-value specific targets, ships,
bridges, railway intersections, road
intersections were were virtually
impossible to hit without significant
collateral damage or considerable waste
of both ordnance and personnel.
>> The problem is the bombs.
Hitting a target with a conventional
dumb bomb relies on the bombing run.
Crews must fly straight and level and
time their release perfectly.
It makes them sitting ducks.
>> And the task facing a young crew
looking at this maelstrom of flak and
searchlights
and aircraft exploding and
perhaps a night fighter coming in. It
was pretty pretty overwhelming.
>> Bomb gone.
>> They face wave after wave of German
fighters, whilst flak [music] and
anti-aircraft rounds fill the air with
lead.
>> I used to put my seat right down and
concentrate on the instruments and try
not to look at Well, what's the point of
looking out? I was flying with damp
feet.
>> You've got no choice.
As long as the bomb aimer is lining up
his target,
you are yourself a target and you really
got no choice but to endure it.
>> Thousands of crew members are lost in
vain.
In 1941, a British report reveals that
only one in four aircraft actually
managed to drop its bombs within 5 mi of
its target.
But one American scientist, B.F.
Skinner, [music]
believes he has the answer.
He thinks he can design the holy grail
of guided bombs, a so-called
fire-and-forget weapon that can be
launched from a safe distance and then
guide itself accurately to the target.
And he has set his sights on one of the
most challenging of all targets,
ships.
Ships are difficult to bomb.
From the air, they're small and a moving
target.
>> In the 20 to 30 seconds it'll take that
bomb to drop, the ship will move.
Those targets are particularly difficult
to hit.
>> The only option is to fly in low.
But there's far more danger of being
shot down, and still the chances of
success is small.
>> If these vessels were at sea, like a
fast destroyer,
uh the the captain that would be
maneuvering it like a like a greyhound.
>> Skinner's bomb will need to track a ship
all the way to impact.
And his answer is extraordinary.
B.F. Skinner is no ordinary scientist.
[music] He's an animal behaviorist, and
he believes that in the search for a
smart bomb, the humble pigeon could be
the perfect guidance system.
They have exceptional eyesight.
Their brains process [music] visual
information much faster than a human's,
and most importantly, they can be
trained.
>> The development and discovery that
Skinner is most known for
um is operant conditioning.
>> Skinner's theory of operant conditioning
is the basis of most forms of animal
training.
It shows how an animal's behavior can be
changed by rewarding it.
>> So, what Skinner brought to us was an
understanding of how
a pigeon could be in some way shaped to
perform various different types of
actions simply by pairing those actions
with some kind of reinforcing or
rewarding event,
such as food.
>> In this way, Skinner teaches his pigeons
ever more complex tasks,
even how to play ping pong,
and how to distinguish between different
shapes made by lights,
pecking only the lights that provide a
reward.
>> One of Skinner's great insights was to
realize that it doesn't just have to be
a light that's going to be paired with
food. It could be anything you want it
to be.
>> Even a battleship.
Skinner thinks he could train a pigeon
to peck at a target ship and design a
bomb that allows those pecks to steer
it.
It may seem eccentric now, but in World
War II, the limits of innovation were
pushed in every conceivable way to gain
an advantage over the enemy.
>> When you think of harnessing creatures
in this crazy way, you might think,
well, why would anybody give money? But
you've got to bear in mind
that at the time, America wanted to
throw everything possible at the enemy.
>> If somebody comes and says, "I can tell
you how a pigeon can drop a bomb on a
target for you."
What are you going to say?
Find out if it's possible.
>> Skinner gets $25,000
to turn a pigeon into a guided missile.
But for this bomb to hit a ship, the
birds will have to be able to track a
moving target.
Skinner begins training his birds to
follow a simple dot, rewarding them just
as before when they get it right.
It works.
And crucially, he's able to show that
once trained, a pigeon can track a
moving object even when subjected to the
noise of explosions and rapid descent.
>> You could put the pigeon under various
different degrees of G and um
atmospheric pressures, and still the
behavior that he trained that in the
pigeon was maintained.
>> Next, Skinner develops a special nose
cone for his pigeon-guided bomb.
The plan is to load three birds into
their own pressurized chambers.
>> Skinner placed pigeons in a sock, which
to a degree would restrain the movements
[music] of the animal, so it couldn't
wander off, flap its wings around. But,
it still had good uh space to move his
head around and peck, importantly, on a
circular screen which was located within
the nose cone of the missile.
>> Lenses and mirrors would project an
image of the target ship from the front
of the bomb onto this translucent
screen.
Inside its pressurized chamber, the
pigeon begins to peck at this projected
image of the target. As it does so, four
valves translate its pecks into
electrical signals, [music] which are
then sent to the control fins of the
bomb.
>> If it pecked dead center, where for
example the battleship might be, then
the the course of the missile would go
uncorrected. But, if the missile started
to go off course, then the image would
also shift and the pecking of the pigeon
would follow it.
>> As the pigeon pecks off center, the
valves send corresponding signals to the
bomb's fins that steer it back towards
the target and bring the ship's image
back [music] to the center of the
screen.
In effect, this allows the pigeon,
albeit unknowingly, to fly the missile
all the way to its target.
Skinner even builds a flight simulator
to test [music] the pigeons' flying
skills. And as this footage shows, they
perform perfectly.
>> He had very, very tight control of his
animal's behavior. He also controlled
the environment in which the animal was
going to be placed upon. So, he could, I
think with a reasonable degree of
certainty, expect the project to
succeed.
>> Prototype bombs are built and legions of
pigeons [music] prepared. Mass
production of the weapons is primed to
start in just 30 days.
But, despite Skinner's success, in 1944,
the military shuts the program down.
>> Unfortunately, I think the reason why it
never was ultimately used is not because
of the psychology of pigeons, but
because of the psychology of people.
It's very, very difficult to place
[music] one's trust in a pigeon.
>> But, it's not the only animal-guided
anti-ship bomb to be proposed.
A cat would be the inspiration for the
next experiments in smart bomb
technology.
During World War II, America's attempts
to make a smart bomb have already
included pigeons and even bats.
Not to be outdone, the US Office of
Strategic [music] Services, ancestor of
the CIA, hits upon another idea.
The cat bomb.
The project is so secret [music] that
still little's known of exactly how it
would have worked, but the theory is
that since cats don't like getting wet
and always land on their feet, if you
harness a cat to a bomb in such a way
that it could steer it and drop it over
open water with a ship in sight, then
perhaps the cat will steer itself and
the bomb towards the dryness of the
ship's deck.
Incredibly, it gets government backing,
but tests don't go well.
One critical problem is that cats aren't
used [music] to looking at water as
they're dropped from a moving aircraft
at 15,000 ft.
>> The problem with the project is probably
whether or not the cat from altitude
recognize the big blue thing that was
approaching it at speed as water. If it
didn't, there'd be no reason for the cat
to realize that it was going to get wet
and therefore guide the missile towards
the target. [music]
>> And unlike pigeons, felines aren't used
to flying, either.
In tests, researchers find the cats have
the unfortunate [music] habit of passing
out mid-drop.
>> Of all the animal projects that I've
heard involving their use in military
activity, I think the the cat bomb has
to be the most crackpot.
>> While the American search [music] for
the smart bomb seems to be faltering,
it's the enemy that draws first blood.
September the 9th, 1943.
A squadron of German Dornier bombers
take off heading for the Italian naval
fleet.
Their job to take it out.
The Italians have just surrendered to
the allies, and under the terms of the
agreement, their ships set sail for
Allied-controlled Malta.
They make it just south of Corsica, but
the Germans, determined to stop them
falling into Allied hands, have [music]
no intention of letting them get any
further.
From 18,000 ft up, the Dorniers set
their sights on the formidable flagship,
[music]
Roma,
and release their bombs.
Two smash through the armored decks of
the Roma and explode inside.
One ignites her magazines, causing a
catastrophic blast that literally splits
her in two.
>> [music]
>> She sinks almost instantly, taking
nearly 1,300 crewmen with her.
Her sister ship, the Italia, [music] is
next.
Badly damaged, she just manages to stay
afloat but is out of action for months.
The allies are amazed.
How could only a few bombers be so
devastating?
They don't realize they've just been
introduced to one of the world's first
guided bombs,
the Fritz X.
>> The world's first smart bombs were
German smart bombs and they were
extremely ingenious. The idea was
that you would carry the bomb up aloft
instead of just dropping it, you would
steer it to its target.
Just think of that.
>> The Fritz X is a huge leap forward in
smart bomb technology.
It doesn't use animals to guide it. It's
radio controlled.
A 3,000 lb bomb, it's fitted with a tail
section with movable fins.
It's designed to be dropped from a
distance of 3 miles while still
approaching its target and from high
altitude around 20,000 ft.
It gathers momentum as it falls reaching
a speed of nearly 700 mph.
Aided by a flare in its tail, the
bombardier directs the Fritz with a
joystick attached to a radio transmitter
which sends guidance signals to the
bomb's tail fins.
By making minor adjustments, the
bombardier can [music] keep the weapon
on track all the way to its target.
The bomb's nose is heavily reinforced,
designed [music] to smash through armor
decks
while a fuse delays detonation until
it's deep inside the ship.
>> The idea being that the bomb would then
explode perhaps in the engine room or
possibly even in the magazine and cause
terrible devastation to the ships.
>> In test drops, a proficient bombardier
could consistently guide the Fritz X to
within 15 ft of its target.
Two days after the sinking of the Roma,
the USS Savannah, one of America's top
light cruisers, is supporting the Allied
landings in Salerno on the Italian
coast, when she too is hit by a German
smart bomb.
The Fritz X smashes through three decks
before exploding, ripping a hole in the
ship's keel and killing nearly 200
sailors.
The crew somehow managed to keep the
Savannah afloat,
but a single bomb has caused massive
damage.
>> It was absolutely devastating. They they
limped the ship back to Malta, where
some repairs were made, and later it was
taken back to America, but it was out of
commission
for months.
>> The attacks are now coming thick and
fast, and a couple of days later, two
British warships are taken out.
Accurate and powerful, the Fritz X is a
force to be reckoned with.
>> As early as 1943, we see the progenitor
of today's smart bombs on the
battlefield and being used properly. Uh
with with considerable tactical success.
>> At first, the Allies are baffled.
How could a bomb be so accurate?
But then they notice something.
>> You could see these things coming, and
and because observers on on the ground
[music] could see the trail behind it,
they knew that these devices were not
simple dumb bombs, that these things
were being controlled.
>> The Allies work out that something is
steering the bombs, and that it must be
the launch aircraft.
They can't stop the bomb traveling at
700 mph, but maybe they can stop the
person guiding it.
>> Once you've dropped the bomb, you have
to sit there in your plane controlling
it until it's hit its target. And the
Allies soon realized that the bomber was
still flying around slowly and keeping
in sight of its target all the time.
>> Once the weapon is released, the bomber
has to slow down to keep it in sight and
guide it to its target.
This makes the plane easy prey for
Allied [music] fighters.
>> It was possible for the aircraft to
escape. It had to loiter,
which put it at considerable risk. The
longer it was there, the longer it was a
target.
>> Once they work it out, Allied fighters
shoot the control aircraft down,
rendering the Fritz X ineffective.
The Germans need a faster, powered
weapon able to target ships quickly and
from further away.
They have it in the Henschel HS 293
glide bomb, the world's first
operational guided missile.
In 1943, the Germans unleashed the
world's first radio-controlled smart
bombs to devastating effect.
But as the Allies exploit their weakness
and target the bomber aircraft, the
Germans know they need a faster, powered
weapon.
Their answer is the Henschel HS 293, the
first ever operational guided missile.
>> The Henschel HS 293
was really a small bomb with a rocket
motor and a pair of wings. And it used
the same radio control system as the
Fritz X.
It was dropped from beneath a plane and
would then fly like a tiny unmanned
drone.
Fly towards its target.
>> The liquid-fueled rocket fires for 10
seconds, accelerating the bomb to more
than 500 mph.
Putting it ahead of the launch aircraft
in clear view of the bomb aimer.
Highly maneuverable, its small wings
give it a range of up to 10 miles.
>> This allowed the airplane to stay a
safer distance away from the fleet, at
least for a little while.
It was the first stand-off weapon.
>> Unlike the Fritz X, which targets heavy
warships, the lighter Henschel is
designed for use against less
well-armored shipping.
>> The HS 293 was focused on transport
ships, landing craft, landing vessels.
It really was a very effective device,
very scary at the time because you could
literally see it coming and you could
see it track you. It would have been
like watching an animal watch you.
>> But the allies have their own engineers
searching for a solution.
As soon as they realize the bombs are
radio-controlled,
they get to work inventing ways to jam
the signals that guide them.
>> The later system that was developed in
the UK was a process that basically
blanketed the air with all of the
frequencies being knocked out. It
basically put a blanket over the
program.
>> By the time of the Normandy landings in
1944,
a combination of effective ship mounted
jammers and Allied air superiority puts
a stop to the reign of the German
radio-guided bombs. But their incredible
accuracy had encouraged the allies to
press on with their own radio-controlled
smart bomb. Designed for a very specific
target, it would see action on [music]
the other side of the world.
1943,
Burma.
Allied troops managed to halt the
relentless advance of the Japanese army
at the frontier with India. But
sustaining the fight in Burma's
impenetrable jungle is tough.
>> Burma is just very, very difficult
country to move anybody and anything in.
>> Keeping troops supplied is the major
challenge for both sides.
While the allies concentrate on resupply
by air,
the Japanese rely on the Burma Railway
that stretches more than 250 miles from
Bangkok in Thailand to Rangoon in Burma
through thick jungle and across numerous
rivers.
If the allies can cut this vital
Japanese supply line, they'll win the
war in Burma.
>> These railways were thin ribbons that
went through the jungle, but they were
vulnerable at the bridges.
The bridges took much longer to repair
and rebuild than a simple roadbed.
Knocking out these bridges was the key
to controlling the battlefield in Burma.
>> But bombing bridges is easier said than
done.
>> Hitting an 8-ft wide target with a with
a bomb from 10,000 ft is largely a
matter of luck.
We needed more than luck if we were
going to take those bridges out.
>> But the US Army Air Force has been
working on a secret weapon specifically
designed for bridge busting.
America's first true smart bomb, the
Azon.
Azon is essentially a 1,000-lb
conventional bomb with a radio [music]
controlled tail bolted onto it.
The tail has four movable surfaces. Two
of them, the ailerons, are controlled
automatically by gyroscope.
They keep the bomb steady as it falls
and stop it from rolling, keeping the
all-important rudder vertical.
The rudder is then controlled left and
right by a bomb aimer using a joystick
connected to a radio controlled
transmitter in the launch aircraft.
Just like with the earlier German bombs,
a flare is fitted to help the bombardier
keep sight of the weapon.
Azon is not as sophisticated as the
German bombs. It can only be steered
left and right, but it's perfect for
static, long, thin targets.
>> Crews receive special training for this
specific [music] purpose in these
aircraft. They were specially equipped.
Eventually, the bombers were
>> [music]
>> assembled into Azon squadrons with the
specific purpose of hitting these
high-value, small targets.
>> The crews practice flying along the
target.
Once the weapon is released, all the
bomb aimer has to do is carefully steer
it left and right to keep it in line.
By 1944,
Azon is ready and deployed [music] to
Burma.
The Azon crews take off bound for the
vital railway bridges.
To buy the crews time to hit their
targets, they have fighter escorts.
The Azon is a hit.
They succeed where hundreds of
conventional bombs had failed.
>> The Azon was perfect for the role that
it was designed for. It was perfect for
bridge busting.
You had to be in control of the air at
the time.
>> As long as you could provide that, you
were going to pretty much hit your
target.
>> The Azon is key in severing the Japanese
supply line.
And by the final Allied counterattacks
of late 1944,
the effect on the enemy is obvious.
>> The Japanese were in some cases close to
starving, and they were desperately
short of equipment, fuel, and
ammunition.
They had nothing else left to fight
with,
and they broke and crumbled.
>> Bombs like the Azon are a huge leap
forward in weapons technology, but
effective as they are, they're not up to
dealing with a new threat to the Allied
war effort.
In 1944, America's number one ally,
Britain, is being terrorized by the
horrifying German V-1 flying bombs.
These frightening devices are frequently
and indiscriminately smashing into
London.
At the same time, German submarines
continue to pose a threat from their
bases in northern France.
America's allies need help targeting V-1
launch sites and submarine pens, but
they're difficult targets, often small
or heavily defended and fortified.
The Azon is not powerful enough.
They need a smart bomb that packs
serious punch.
1944,
London, England.
A city under constant attack from the
Germans' latest weapon, the terrifying
V1 flying bomb.
Their submarines continue to target
Allied ships from their heavily
fortified bases in northern France.
Striking back at V1 launch sites and
submarine pens is a top priority,
but they're not easy targets.
>> All of these targets were either hard to
find, so they required pinpoint
precision,
or they were so heavily emplaced that
they required massive [music] explosive
potential to knock them out.
>> The Americans need a weapon that's
powerful and accurate.
Their top-secret plan is to [music] take
unmanned aircraft, pack them with
explosives, and then crash [music] them
by radio control into these fortified or
hard-to-find targets.
The operation is code-named Aphrodite.
>> The aircraft that were selected were
war-weary bombers. They had seen many
missions already. They'd already seen
their combat duty. They were due to be
retired from service.
The aircraft were stripped of all of
their operational gear, weapons, seats,
armor, pretty much anything that would
add additional weight would be removed
from the aircraft.
>> The planes are then packed full with
[music] high explosives, weighing more
than double their normal payload, and
creating one massive flying bomb.
Two radio control units adapted from the
Azon bomb are then fitted to the
cockpit,
allowing this drone to be controlled
from a second mothership aircraft.
The whole thing [music] would be linked
together using a revolutionary new
technology,
television.
>> They then fitted
two television cameras. One of them
looked down at the dashboard, at the
control panel.
And the other television camera looked
out at the nose.
>> The images are transmitted back to the
accompanying mothership aircraft,
allowing the bomb aimer to see exactly
where his drone is going.
>> Using the a television system to help
you guide the aircraft was potentially a
deal maker when it came to finding a
perfect way to create a true standoff
weapon.
>> But early tests reveal a problem.
Revolutionary though the technology is,
it's not advanced enough to get an
unmanned aircraft into the air while
heavily loaded with high explosives.
The drones need pilots.
They need two volunteers for each drone
to take the aircraft up, arm the
explosives, pass control to the
mothership, and then bail out while
still over England.
It's incredibly dangerous.
>> With all of those potential ignition
sources, with all the chances of sparks,
and all of that explosive
uh intended to make a really large hole
in the ground someplace,
the the recipe for disaster was always
present.
>> One volunteer for the Navy's version of
Aphrodite, Operation Anvil, is
experienced bomber pilot Lieutenant
Joseph Kennedy Jr. [music]
Elder brother to John Fitzgerald
Kennedy.
But it's Joseph who is the [music] man
the Kennedy family is grooming for the
future presidency.
>> He'd had a very successful career and
was due to be rotated home after
completing the maximum allowed number of
missions.
Instead, he volunteered for service in
the Aphrodite program.
>> On August the 12th, 1944,
Kennedy and [music] his co-pilot take
off in a drone loaded with more than
20,000 lb of high explosive.
Their target is a heavily fortified
V-weapon site in northern France.
They get the plane up to the 2,000-ft
operating height and transfer control to
the mothership.
But before they could bail out,
Kennedy's plane disappears in a huge
fireball.
The enormous explosion scatters burning
wreckage over 2 square miles.
The pilots' bodies are never found.
>> It's hard not to admire the bravery, the
commitment, the dedication of the
professionals that that went into those
very dangerous situations.
>> The missions continued for another 5
months after Kennedy's [music] death.
Several pilots are killed.
The operation doesn't hit a single
target.
>> Radios failed, the televisions would
fail, the target areas were so heavily
defended that these low-flying,
relatively slow bombers were easy prey
for anti-aircraft guns.
>> Only one of the planes ever got near its
target
and it didn't explode.
And therefore gave the Germans all of
the instrumentation and all of the
control details that the Americans
didn't want them to have.
>> In January 1945, the operation is
cancelled.
Eventually considered more hazardous to
the crews than to their targets.
In the end, the technology of World War
II isn't yet good enough to create the
perfect smart bomb.
>> They were, in theory, brilliant weapons
and it was a great idea. It's just that
the the the sheer technical complexity
prevented it from working.
>> But soon the search is back on.
In the 1950s, more sophisticated bombs
based on the Azon see action in Korea.
And it's in Vietnam that smart bombs
really take off.
Operational TV-guided bombs are
introduced. The technique pioneered in
the Aphrodite drones.
Laser guidance also makes its debut. For
the first time, pilots can strike a
target that's marked from the air or
[music] ground using a laser beam.
The bomb following the laser's
reflection to strike with massive
firepower and impressive accuracy.
By the first Gulf War in 1991,
the smart bomb has come of age.
>> You got to see it every night on the
evening news, sometimes almost real
time.
>> Reporters in Baghdad in 1991 spoke of a
sensation of being on a chessboard and a
massive hand would come down and remove
a piece.
Shock and awe.
>> Today, bombs guided by satellites can
destroy targets with pinpoint accuracy
from miles away without a pilot ever
seeing his target.
Their evolution can be traced directly
to the World War II innovators who
pushed the limits of their technology
and imagination in their race to defeat
the enemy.